Guide to the Stanford Historical Society Oral History Program Interviews SC0932
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Faculty and Staff Interviews, 2007-2016; Series 5
  - Pizzo, Philip A., 2016
    Pizzo begins his narrative in New York City, where he was the first in his working-class family to graduate from high school. Like many first-generation Americans, Pizzo says, his family encouraged him to become a doctor and to “become something.” His reading, especially the book Microbe Hunters by Paul de Kruif and biographies of great scientists and thinkers, also drew him to the field of medicine, as did the historical context of the Vietnam War. Recounting the challenges and contributions of his years at Fordham University, the University of Rochester Medical School, and the elite Boston Children’s Hospital, Pizzo outlines how his career embraced both research and clinical practice in pediatric oncology and infectious disease.
    Pizzo describes receiving a summons to join the National Institutes of Health in 1973 and devotes considerable attention to his two decades there and especially to the young patients who influenced the direction of his research. First came ten-year-old Ted DeVita, who was confined to an isolation room because of a severely compromised immune system. That relationship, Pizzo points out, prepared him for the challenges of HIV and AIDS. By then the NIH chief of pediatrics, Pizzo explains that research in pediatric AIDS led to the development of continuous infusion therapy, which “made a pretty big splash” at the International AIDS Meeting in Stockholm in 1988. His growing reputation drew Elizabeth Glaser to Pizzo and NIH. He describes treating her two AIDS-infected children, as well as collaboration with Elizabeth and his admiration for her work as founder of the Pediatric AIDS Foundation.
    Seeking a new direction for his career as he turned 50, Pizzo discusses his brief return to Boston Children’s Hospital before Stanford made an irresistible offer in 2000. Pizzo recalls the long deliberative process that resulted in his acceptance of the job as dean of the School of Medicine. The school and the two hospitals were experiencing considerable divisiveness at the time because of the failed merger with the University of California, San Francisco. Healing the wounds of that venture is what Pizzo sees as his first major challenge at Stanford, and he identifies the faculty’s revolt against the UCSF project as the most important element in its failure. He recounts in detail the issues involved in reconciling the School’s academic and clinical perspectives and his successful efforts to rebuild faculty morale and create an agenda to focus their energy toward the future. Pizzo also discusses outreach to the other academic schools at Stanford, resulting in the founding of the Department of Bioengineering. He describes initiatives that brought needed resources to the medical facilities and revitalized the way they worked together, including the beginning of the institutes, diversity initiatives, and fundraising programs.
    Pizzo declares himself proud of the community that now exists in Stanford’s medical establishment, the care it provides to patients, and the national recognition it has achieved.
  - Quinn, Helen R., 2014-10-07
    Helen R. Quinn begins with her childhood growing up in Australia and how that experience, including intellectual discussions with her father and brothers, influenced her in life. Her family moved to the United States when she was college age. Quinn continues with her experiences at Stanford as a student and her decision to pursue a degree in physics. She talks about being a female in a largely male world. She recalls her experiences as a married student and as a post-doctoral fellow in Germany, followed by her experience at SLAC on her return to Stanford. She covers a variety of other topics, including the Paccei-Quinn Symmetry, tenure track issues, family life, women’s issues, salary inequities, her contributions in the field of physics and her awards. She concludes with her work in K-12 science education.
  - Raffel, Sidney, 2012 Apr 15
    Over the course of three interviews, Dr. Sidney Raffel discussed much of his professional and personal life. He began with his parents’ immigration stories from Riga, Latvia, and outside Vilnius, Lithuania, and a brief description of his own early education. Dr. Raffel then spoke about his educational experiences at Johns Hopkins and Duke, before moving to Stanford for further medical training and a career teaching, researching, and practicing medicine in Stanford’s Medical school. During his tenure at Stanford, he was Dean of the Medical School and Chairman of the Department of Medical Microbiology. He discussed some of his research topics, like poliomyelitis, tuberculosis, and mononucleosis. The interviews also encompassed some of his publications and work off-campus during sabbaticals and fellowships. The conversation concluded with a look at some of his activity during his lengthy retirement, including a passion for painting.
    Born in 1911 in Baltimore, MD, to immigrant parents, Sidney Raffel graduated from Johns Hopkins University with a Bachelor of Science degree in 1930. In 1933, he added a ScD. in Immunology, also from Johns Hopkins. He initially came to Stanford in 1935 with a one-year fellowship to study poliomyelitis, but he stayed on as an assistant instructor in the Medical School, completing his MD at Stanford in 1942. His career at Stanford lasted until his retirement around the years of the Vietnam War Protests on campus, though it also included sabbaticals to teach at prestigious international institutions like the University of Edinburgh, University of Kyoto, and the University of Shiraz. In 1949 he had a Guggenheim Fellowship in Basel, Switzerland. Dr. Raffel’s career at Stanford included over twenty years as Chair of the Department of Medical Microbiology and Immunology and two years as Acting Dean of the Medical School.
    Among his many honors are a 1988 Society of Scholars Award and a 1992 J.E. Wallace Sterling Award for Distinguished Teaching. Dr. Raffel also wrote many articles, lectures, and editions one and two of the textbook Immunity. He has participated in NIH advisory panels, the Stanford Faculty Senate, and many other important organizations.
    Dr. Sidney Raffel married Yvonne Fay (1909-2001) in 1938. She was a Public Health Nurse for Stanford at the time. They had five daughters. Dr. Raffel continues to live on the Stanford campus, and spends his time reading scientific journals and enjoying painting with oils.
    Access to Collection
    Audio restricted unitl 2033.
  - Ramsaur, Michael F., 2010 Oct 14
    Professor Ramsaur begins his story with his recruitment to Stanford in 1971 as a young man of 23 with a wife and child. His personal development, changes and growth from 1971 to the time of his oral history interviews are parallel in many ways to the changes and shifts of the MFA program at Stanford. He starts by describing the program in 1971, the abrupt shift in focus when Professor Charles Lyons was appointed chair, and the social and technological issues that influenced him, his students, and the department over the years. He discusses the differences between the undergraduate and graduate programs. He mentions the role of the Stanford Institute for Creativity and Arts and how it has funded various projects, including a recent project in a small village in Uganda. Professor Ramsaur discusses his participation in international projects, including projects in Prague and China. He also talks about the history of the Committee for Black Performing Arts and the Institute for Diversity in the Arts.
    In the second interview, he gives fuller insight into the topics covered in the previous interview. He concludes with a discussion of the influences of new technologies and changes in thinking about performing arts, including aerial dancing and experiential performing.
    Michael F. Ramsaur is a professor at Stanford University serving as Director of Production. In addition to teaching regularly at the Bavarian Theater Academy Munich, he is a guest professor at the University of Arts Belgrade in the Interdisciplinary M.A. Program in Theater, and an honorary professor at the Central Academy of Drama Beijing. He serves as President of OISTAT (the International Association of Scenographers, Theater Architects, and Technicians), and is a long-time active member of USITT, as well as a member of the United Scenic Artist Association (Lighting Design USAA Local #829), the International Alliance Theatrical Stage Employees (Stage Hands IATSE Local #16), the Illumination Engineering Society of North America (IESNA), and the International Association Lighting Designers (IALD).
    Ramsaur has had a forty-year career in theater including serving as a lighting designer for many theater companies internationally and locally, including Broadway by the Bay, where he is Resident Lighting Designer. Examples of his designs have been displayed at two United States Institute of Theater Technology Design Expositions, a theater design exhibit at the Triton Museum San Jose, and at theatrical design exhibitions in Prague and Shanghai.
    He has been awarded Outstanding Lighting Design awards from the San Francisco Bay Area Critics Association, Dean Goodman Award, and Drama Logue Award as well as receiving a Fulbright grant. His articles on lighting techniques have been published in three countries and he has created a computerized software program to aid lighting designers.
  - Reaven, Gerald M., 2015
    The first part of the interview begins with Reaven’s decision to attend the University of Chicago for his undergraduate and medical degrees and what drew him to research. He recounts how the military’s use of the draft to recruit doctors influenced his decision to take a research fellowship at Stanford and recalls his, and his family’s, experiences when he was stationed in Germany.
    He contrasted his impressions of Stanford’s hospital (then located in San Francisco) with the University of Chicago’s medical program and why he chose to do his residency at the University of Michigan. However, the change in direction of the Stanford medical school program -- both in the five year curriculum for students and the recruitment of full time professors to teach and see patients -- and the relocation of the hospital drew him back. He reminisces on the atmosphere at Stanford during this time as well as how he set up his lab and collaborated with fellow Stanford professor, Charles Lucas.
    Reaven discusses what led him to his experiments that proved type II diabetes was due to insulin insensitivity, as opposed to lack of insulin in the blood, and how his research progressed. He recalls how he chose the topic of his famous Banting Lecture and the resulting awareness into the link between insulin insensitivity and increased risk of the individual to strokes and heart attacks.
    The second interview focuses on Reaven’s administration experience with several divisions within the medical school and how he came to be the director of the Geriatric Research, Education and Clinical Center at the VA hospital, where he was able to implement “unconventional medical training.” He discusses his wife’s academic career (Eve Reaven holds a PhD in anatomy and worked as a professor at Stanford) and how they balanced careers and family. Reaven also recounts his work with committees to promote gender equality in medical admissions and tenure appointments, and what Stanford was like in the 1960’s.
  - Rebholz, Ronald A., 2013 Jun 5, 18
    Professor Rebholz opens the first session by briefly discussing his early life in St. Louis, his family and their importance in his life, his education in both public and catholic schools, and his time in the army. He discusses his year of graduate study at Stanford before entering the army, and his time as a Rhodes Scholar at Oxford, where he eventually earned his D.Phil. He goes on to cover his arrival at Stanford in 1961, and his frustration over the firing of Bruce Franklin, a colleague in the English Department. He discusses faculty members and the departmental culture of the time, his classes and teaching, and his experience as department chair.
    The second session starts with Professor Rebholz noting the importance of departmental administrative staff. He goes on to recount his time on Stanford’s Academic Senate, including his interactions with university presidents. He discusses his work with John Manley and their shared disapproval of the Hoover Institution and vehement opposition to the Reagan Library and Research Center. He also discusses his involvement in instituting the Western Culture courses and the need for students to develop both analytical and writing skills. Professor Rebholz notes other issues he raised on campus, including the university’s relationship to Webb Ranch and unionizing Stanford employees. The interview moves on to awards Professor Rebholz received, as well as his thoughts on both the growth of and changes at Stanford in terms of the campus and the community.
  - Reimers, Niels J., 2015-07-02
    Niels J. Reimers, founder and former director of Stanford University's Office of Technology Licensing (OTL), begins his interview describing his family and living in Norway and Carmel, California. He describes his student days at Stanford and Oregon State as a mechanical engineering major, and he reflects on the three years he spent in the Navy on the USS Bon Homme Richard.
    Reimers also discusses his experience as an industrial engineer at Ampex and his transition into marketing at Philco Western Development Laboratories (later Philco-Ford) where he learned about contract law and how to develop new products from scratch. Reimers recounts his work as lead negotiator for Ford Aeronutronic on a contract change to the Reentry Management Program with the US Air Force and his departure from industry.
    Reimers describes his return to Stanford as Associate Director of Research Administration and his early interest in commercializing research inventions. He speaks of the system present at Stanford when he arrived in which there was no organized patent program. Inventions were sent to an outside company, Research Corporation, for licensing, and Stanford received minimal royalty income. Reimers describes the creation and approval of the pilot program for the Office of Technology Licensing and the development of a new royalty distribution system.
    He remembers the inventors and inventions he worked with, including Bill Johnson’s synthetic juvenile growth hormone for pest control, John Chowning’s work with altering the perceptual location of sound in space for electronic keyboards, Stan Cohen’s plasmid and Herb Boyer’s restriction enzyme which led to recombinant DNA, and Art Schawlow’s lasers for erasing.
    Reimers goes on to describe the autonomy he had managing OTL, his relationship with various deans of research, and working through potential conflicts of interest for inventors. He also discusses how OTL’s entrepreneurial model set it apart from other universities.
    Reimers recounts his involvement with the Bayh-Dole bill, which gave universities the right to the results of their research. He later reflects on his time spent at MIT, the University of California,Berkley, and the University of California, San Francisco (UCSF) working to help them reform their technology licensing programs.
    Reimers concludes the interview by summarizing his experience at Stanford, reminiscing about the research discoveries he came across, and reflecting on changes in the administration at Stanford, his retirement, and his activities after he left Stanford.
  - Richter, Burton, 2014 May 5-8
    Burton “Burt” Richter begins his interviews by discussing his childhood in the boroughs of New York City and his early education at Mercersburg Academy in Pennsylvania. He then moves on to his time as an undergraduate and graduate student at Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) as well as his academic turn toward physics under the tutelage of Francis Bitter and Francis Friedman. He discusses his brief stint at Brookhaven National Laboratory and his return to MIT, where he completed his evolution into a particle physicist and carried out his PhD research.
    Richter next discusses his recruitment to a postdoc position at the High Energy Physics Lab at Stanford by Wolfgang Panofsky. Richter describes his role in the design and construction of the first electron-electron colliding beam machine at Stanford and his early years as a postdoc and later an assistant professor in the Physics Department at Stanford. Richter goes on to discuss the technical and bureaucratic challenges that ultimately led to the construction of the electron-positron collider and the resulting watershed research in November 1974 that led to his Nobel Prize in Physics. He also discusses the foresight of Sebastian Doniach and William Spicer to request the electron-positron collider be constructed in such a way as to release the x-rays and in so doing create a line of research that grew to become the Stanford Synchrotron Radiation Laboratory (SSRL). He further notes that their research not only revolutionized condensed matter physics, but also birthed Keith Hodgson’s structural biology program.
    Richter also discusses his yearlong sabbatical at CERN and the research that led up to the construction of the Linear Collider Project. He then elaborates on this time as lab director at SLAC under Panofsky mentorship, and finally his years as Director of the Stanford Linear Accelerator Center (SLAC). He also comments on the variety of research programs which were started during his time at Stanford, including, the Linac Coherent Light Source (LCLS), the Fixed Target Program, the Stanford Synchrotron Radiation Lightsource (SSRL), and the Positron-Electron-Proton (PEP) Storage Ring. Richter concludes the interview by discussing his interest and recent work in climate and energy policy, which began in the mid-1990s and expanded when he stepped down as Director of SLAC in 1999.
  - Rosenberg, Saul A., 2016-03-09
    Saul A. Rosenberg pioneered treatments for lymphoma and other cancers in the early 1960s, and his work helped to establish the field of medical oncology. He collaborated with Henry Kaplan to run the first random clinical trials for lymphoma and Hodgkin’s lymphoma. Rosenberg gives a candid interview about the setbacks and serendipitous opportunities in his pursuit of a medical career in internal medicine and oncology that culminated in a decades-long career at the Stanford University School of Medicine.
    He begins the interview by describing his background as a poor Jewish kid growing up in Cleveland, Ohio, the first of his family to go to college. Rosenberg recounts his plan to enter medical school at the age of 18 to avoid being drafted for World War II and the personal and bureaucratic obstacles that caused him to drop out as an undergrad. This apparent misfortune, he explains, led to a lab technician position in Hymer Friedell’s Atomic Energy Medical Research Project, which in turn gave him unique and sought-after skills in radiology and put him in contact with numerous researchers when he did enter medical school at Western Reserve University.
    He recalls another seeming setback--being drafted to serve as a marine doctor--which interfered with his pursuit of a PhD but made him realize that he wanted to practice clinical medicine. He discusses his residency at Peter Bent Brigham Hospital, where he was made chief resident and spent a year researching lymphomas in Lloyd Craver’s lab. He goes into detail about an influential paper he wrote: a statistical analysis of 1,269 lymphomas, which was made possible by an early IBM punch-card computer.
    Rosenberg discusses how, despite these accomplishments, he had a difficult time finding an academic position that would allow him to work with radiotherapies and internal medicine until Kaplan and Halsted Holman made a place for him at Stanford where he eventually held professorships in both medicine and radiation.
    He began working at Stanford just as the medical school was relocating from San Francisco to the Stanford campus. He describes how his hospital experience was put to use by Holman as they developed their clinical program and how he eventually took over the role of physician-in-chief. He opines about what made the new medical school such a delight to work in and how more recent changes have diminished it. He talks about job offers he did not take and the failed merger with the University of California San Francisco, as well as his position on Stanford’s Advisory Board.
    Rosenberg then goes into detail about the work that made him famous: his collaboration with Kaplan that revolutionized lymphoma--and specifically Hodgkin’s lymphoma--treatments, turning a terminal diagnosis to one of hope. He describes how Kaplan’s cutting- edge linear accelerator, as well as his own clinical expertise, improved patient care and allowed them to begin randomized clinical trials. Rosenberg muses on his personal relationship with Kaplan and mentions Kaplan’s children and their careers.
    Finally, Rosenberg deliberates about what he feels are his real contributions: his children, his students, and his patients. He describes himself as a tree trunk that supports the beautiful leaves and flowers that are his former students’ accomplishments and careers. And he takes humble joy in knowing that through his medical administrations, his patients have lived longer, and often remarkable, lives.
  - Ryan, Lawrence V., 2009 Feb 13
    Professor Lawrence V. Ryan discussed his career at Stanford University from 1952 to 1988 as a professor of English. At the time of his retirement, he was also the Atha Professor of the Humanities. Professor Ryan specialized in the study of Renaissance literature, primarily that of England but also with a secondary emphasis on Medieval and Renaissance Italian humanism. Professor Ryan also discussed his work with John Goheen, Professor of Philosophy, and Mark Mancall, Professor of History, to found the Structured Liberal Education program, an intellectually rigorous interdisciplinary program at Stanford. Professor Ryan was awarded the Lloyd W. Dinkelspiel Award for 1974-75 for outstanding service to undergraduate education.
  - Schimke, Robert T., 2012 Mar 12
    During the interview, Professor Schimke discussed his early life and family background, and continued with a description of his education. He described classmates, courses, and colleagues from his time as an undergraduate at Stanford and on through his time in medical school and residency at Massachusetts General. From there, Professor Schimke explained how he came to return to Stanford in the department of Pharmacology and later, his move to the department of Biological Sciences. The interview included Professor Schimke’s assessment of the medical school and the academic departments in which he taught, and he pointed out both strengths and weaknesses, charting the progress over time. He explained some of his research on cancer, including explorations of proteins in egg whites and also the chemical methotrexate, used in chemotherapy. The interview concluded with a discussion of Professor Schimke’s art, from his earliest endeavors back in grade school to the development and experimentation in the years since being hit by a car while biking in 1995, an accident which left him with limited mobility.